<SkyHighSyllabus version="3.0">


    <ResourceLibrary>
        <Asset id="IMG-CHUTE1" type="image">
            <Description>Diagram of a modern skydiving rig with main and reserve containers highlighted.</Description>
            <Context>Use this to introduce the dual canopy concept.</Context>
        </Asset>
        <Asset id="IMG-CHUTE-HANDLES1" type="image">
            <Description>Close-up of the main ripcord and reserve (silver) handles on a student harness.</Description>
            <Context>Use this when discussing emergency procedures or gear checks.</Context>
        </Asset>
        <Asset id="IMG-ALTIMETER1" type="image">
            <Description>An analog altimeter face showing the 'Yellow' (caution) and 'Red' (deployment) zones.</Description>
            <Context>Use this to introduce the student to altimeters.</Context>
        </Asset>
		<Asset id="IMG-DECWINDOW1" type="image">
            <Description>A diagram showing the decision window from 5000ft AGL to 3000ft AGL</Description>
            <Context>Crucial for teaching altitude awareness and the 3000ft manadtatory deployment height</Context>
        </Asset>
		<Asset id="VID-CUNIM1" type="video">
            <Description>An video of cumulonimbus cloud formations.</Description>
            <Context>Used to show students what these type of clouds look like.</Context>
        </Asset>
		<Asset id="VID-LOWCLOUD1" type="video">
            <Description>An video of low cloud over a drop zone</Description>
            <Context>Used to illustate how low cloud dandgerously reduces visibility and manouvering options.</Context>
        </Asset>
		<Asset id="IMG-WATERDANGER1" type="image">
            <Description>An image of a parachute in the water with a jumper beneath it</Description>
            <Context>Used as a visual aid to reinforce the danger of cocooning and entanglement.</Context>
        </Asset>
		<Asset id="IMG-WATERLAND1" type="image">
            <Description>A diagram of the correct water landing approach, including airborne chest strap release and leg strap release on water contact.</Description>
            <Context>Visual aid for the water landinmg procedure.</Context>
        </Asset>
		<Asset id="VID-ARCH1" type="video">
            <Description>A short video clip demonstrating a skydiver adopting the stable arch position in freefall.</Description>
            <Context>Visual aid for teaching the stable arch position.</Context>
        </Asset>
    </ResourceLibrary>
	
	
	<Config>
        <course_title>SkyHigh Elementary Parachute Training</course_title>
    </Config>
	
	
    <Module id="MOD-01" title="Equipment">
        
		<Lesson id="GEAR-01" title="Dual Canopy System">
            <Theory>
                Skydiving rigs contain two parachutes: a Main and a Reserve.
				These should be inspected yearly.				
                The system is designed for total reliability.
				
            </Theory>
            <KeyPoints>
                The container (the backpack) protects the canopies until deployment.
                The reserve is packed by a certified rigger.
				RULE: Never jump without a reserve.
				Main Ripcord: Located right side, chest height. Pull outwards with right-hand, not crossbody.
				Reserve Handle: Silver Handle, Located left side, hip height.
				Protocol: Reserve usage only permitted after a Main Cut-away, using the standard cutaway procedure. (Covered later in emergency procedures)
            </KeyPoints>
			<PrimaryResources>
				IMG-CHUTE1
				IMG-CHUTE-HANDLES1				
			</PrimaryResources>			
        </Lesson>
        
        <Lesson id="GEAR-02" title="Altimeter">
            <Theory>
                The altimeter is your primary safety instrument. It measures height above the dropzone landing area. Wrist mounted and easy to read.
            </Theory>
            <Procedure>
				CALIBRATION: Always set Altimeter so that zero matches dropzone elevation.
                CHECK CADENCE: You MUST check your altimeter every 5 seconds during freefall.
            </Procedure>
			<PrimaryResources>
				IMG-ALTIMETER1			
			</PrimaryResources>	
        </Lesson>
    
	</Module>
	
	
    <Module id="MOD-02" title="Standard Procedures">
	
        <Lesson id="SOP-01" title="Environmental Checks">
            <Theory>We need to check that environmental conditions are safe to jump. These can be verified both visually, and via TAF reports.</Theory>
            <DangerConditions>
				Cumulonimmbus: These clouds can be lethal for jumpers due to updrafts, turbulence, rain, hail etc. Jumping is prohibited if there are cumulonimbus clouds within 10 miles of the dropzone.
				Cloud Cover: No boarding if cloud cover is below 2,000ft AGL
				Max Wind Speed at DZ: Maximum ground wind speed at drop zone is 20 knots
			</DangerConditions>
			<PrimaryResources>
				VID-CUNIM1
				VID-LOWCLOUD1
			</PrimaryResources>	
        </Lesson>
		
		<Lesson id="SOP-02" title="Aircraft Exit Procedure">
            <Theory>A clean exit sets up a stable freefall, and prevents "Tumble" malfunctions. NOTE: use the VID-ARCH1 as a video to demonstrate the position.</Theory>
            <Action>Maintain the 'Banana' stable arch in freefall: hips pushed forward, head back, arms symmetrical</Action>
			<PrimaryResources>
				VID-ARCH1
			</PrimaryResources>	
        </Lesson>
		
    </Module>
	
	
	
	
	<ReferenceLibrary id="USPA-SIM-2026">
        <Section title="General Lessons">
            Flight Cycle
			A flight cycle is the parachute’s response during the period of time between an input
			and the parachute’s return to stabilized full flight. It is important to understand how a
			flight cycle is created so that you can avoid entering one close to the ground just before
			landing. Flaring for landing is a one-way street, meaning you can stop pulling down
			the toggles at any point during the flare stroke if you started it too high, but you cannot
			go back up.
			Any input to a canopy, such as turning or pulling down the toggles and letting them
			back up, initiates a flight cycle. The flight cycle is a normal and predictable flight characteristic of all parachutes. When a flight cycle occurs, the parachute dives, its speed
			increases beyond that of full flight, and the jumper swings back behind the parachute.
			The parachute then slows down as the jumper swings forward under the parachute and
			it returns to full flight.
			Experiencing a flight cycle up high can be fun. However, a flight cycle just before or
			during a flare is dangerous because the parachute dives forward and picks up speed,
			and the effectiveness of the flare is greatly reduced. This is why the proper response to
			a flare initiated too high is to stop and hold whenever you realize it is too high, then finish
			the flare forcefully when closer to the ground.
			Make no more than two attempts or take no longer than 5 seconds, whichever comes
			first, before initiating emergency procedures.
			● Premature container opening in freefall: Attempt to locate and deploy the pilot
			chute first. If you can’t locate the pilot chute after two tries or 5 seconds, or if deploying
			the pilot chute results in a partial malfunction, cut away and deploy the reserve.
			● Lost deployment handle: Place your hand on the side of the container and slide it
			down to the bottom corner. Find the pilot chute and deploy. If you cannot find the
			pilot chute after two tries or 5 seconds, initiate emergency procedures.
			● Hard pull: Place your elbow against the container for leverage. If you cannot throw
			the pilot chute after two tries or 5 seconds, initiate emergency procedures.
			● Pilot-chute hesitation: Modify the airflow by twisting slightly while looking over
			your right shoulder. If that doesn’t work, repeat over your left shoulder. If the pilot
			chute does not launch after two tries or 5 seconds, initiate emergency procedures.
			Static-line students: Your instructor will review the student-in-tow procedures,
			which are: Arch and signal to your instructor that you are ready for them to cut your
			static line. After the static line is cut, deploy your reserve.
			Remember these critical altitudes: You must decide to cut away by 2,500 feet and
			then act immediately. Also, if you find yourself below 1,000-foot cutaway hard deck
			without a functioning canopy, deploy the reserve without cutting away.
			With your instructor, practice in the training harness to recognize and respond to
			problems and malfunctions using guidance from Category A—Academics in the
			first-jump-course topics.
			At airports, normal flight practices separate aircraft traffic from parachute traffic,
			but you need to respect runways and aircraft landing patterns. Your instructor will
			explain your drop zone’s policies about avoiding runways while flying your canopy and
			after you’ve landed. 
			A. Exit and Freefall
			For Review
			Review the climb-out and exit procedures. Improving your setup, launch, and flyaway
			on each jump will prepare you for a solo exit in Category D.
			Review the altitude and body position awareness procedure HAALR. First recognize
			your heading to confirm you are not turning. Know your altitude by reading the altimeter (AFF and tandem) or counting from exit (IAD and static line). Arch at the hips to
			improve belly-to-wind stability. Check your leg position—extended to 45 degrees with
			toes pointed—and adjust as needed. Relax by taking a breath in and out, letting go of
			unwanted body tension.
			IAD and static-line students: HAALR might be new to you, as this applies only after
			you’ve made a successful clear and pull.
			The goal in freefall for Category C is to refine your neutral body position so you can fall
			straight down in a column of air. You achieve this by maintaining a heading in a relaxed,
			neutral position. You should also increase your altitude awareness and initiate a solo
			pull sequence at your assigned altitude.
			Review how to maintain a heading which includes:
			● Pick a heading reference in front of you and keep your eyes on it.
			● Use HAALR to remain in a relaxed neutral body position and altitude aware.
			● Use the skill of starting and stopping turns from Category B to stop unintentional
			turns on Category C jumps.
			New Stuff
			AFF students: If you now have only one AFF instructor, the instructor will revise the
			climb-out procedure for your exit. With one instructor, you may prepare for slightly
			different results after the launch, as it typically flies vertically a little longer than it
			would with two instructors.
			AIR: The freefall rule for Category A and B was: if your AFF instructors are not with you,
			you must pull immediately. This rule changes for Category C and forward. Now that you
			have demonstrated awareness and stability, your instructors may release you during
			the freefall. The new rule is: if you are Altitude aware, In control, and Relaxed (AIR), you
			may continue in freefall and deploy at the assigned altitude. However, if you are not
			Altitude aware, In control, and Relaxed (AIR), you have only 5 seconds to fix it. If unsuccessful after 5 seconds, deploy your main canopy immediately.
			Turbulence on Landing
			Turbulence is disturbed air that can affect canopy flight and integrity. Due to obstacles
			and wind direction, turbulence sometimes occurs in the landing area. The effects and
			likelihood of turbulence increase with the wind speed. Understanding and predicting
			turbulence will allow you to make safe landing choices. Managing unexpected turbulence on landing is an important skill, but avoiding a landing in turbulence is the best
			plan for safe landings.
			Mechanical turbulence is caused by buildings, trees, and hilly or mountainous terrain.
			Anticipate turbulence 10 to 20 times the height of an obstacle on its downwind side.
			Wake turbulence is the swirling air currents left behind a moving object from the disturbed airflow caused by its motion, such as wingtip vortices for aircraft. For example,
			a canopy that lands just before you can generate an invisible wake behind them, which
			can linger especially in low-wind conditions. You can even find wake turbulence downwind of the propeller wash of an aircraft landing on the runway.
			Thermal turbulence is caused by thermals, which are pockets of warm air that rise due
			to the uneven heating of the ground given differences in terrain. The air over certain
			surfaces such as asphalt, plowed fields, or rocky terrain heats up faster than over other
			surfaces. As the warmer air rises then mixes with surrounding cooler air, irregularities
			produce unexpected updrafts and downdrafts.
			When flying in turbulence at any altitude, maintain the desired heading using smooth
			but effective toggle input. Fly in full flight unless the canopy’s owner’s manual directs
			otherwise. If there is turbulence near the ground, prepare to respond quickly with a
			forceful flare and a PLF.
			Turbulence can create a flight cycle. Category B introduced the concept of the flight
			cycle to reinforce that flaring for landing is a one-way street, meaning you can always
			stop pulling down the toggles at any point during the flare stroke, but cannot go back
			up. Letting your toggles back up during your flare for landing will cause a flight cycle.
			Turbulent or gusty winds on landing can also initiate a flight cycle, causing your parachute to dive toward the ground. If this happens just before the flare, the effectiveness
			of the flare diminishes. Because the flight cycle will cause you to swing back from underneath the parachute as it dives and picks up speed, you must flare forcefully to get back
			under the parachute and in a position for landing. To help you recognize a flight cycle
			and respond effectively, you will perform a flight-cycle drill in this category and practice
			a forceful flare when in a flight cycle.
			Improving your Landing
			Downwind landings are better than low turns. On calm days, unexpected wind shifts
			sometimes require you to land with the wind, instead of against it. Sometimes, jumpers
			become confused about the pattern and don’t realize they are set up for a downwind
			landing until they’re on final approach. When faced with deciding between a low turn or
			a downwind landing, apply your landing priorities and choose to land downwind. When
			making a downwind landing, flare at the normal altitude, regardless of ground speed,
			and PLF.
			Flaring for landing can take a few seconds, so dissecting the parts of the flare can increase your awareness
			and improve your flare for better landings. During the
			flare, you are converting forward speed to lift. Flare
			the canopy quickly to the first stage to slow down and
			swing under your canopy, flattening the glide. Continue the flare to keep the flat glide. Continue flaring
			smoothly and completely until landing
			To prevent an open parachute in the aircraft, take care when you’re leaning back
			against anything. Move carefully when you’re near or outside the door. If a parachute
			opens in the plane and the door is closed, secure the parachute, notify your instructor
			and land with the plane. If the door is open, contain the parachute, close the door, and
			land with the plane. If the parachute goes out the door, follow immediately to prevent
			endangering yourself and others. A pre-jump gear check shortly before leaving the aircraft is essential to prevent these occurrences.
			If landing off the DZ is unavoidable, look for an open, clear, accessible field as early as
			possible. Decide on an alternate landing area by 2,000 feet. Be aware that power lines
			often run along roads and between buildings, as well as randomly in open fields. A
			row of vegetation often hides a fence. Rocks, hills, and other terrain irregularities often
			remain invisible until just prior to touchdown. Inspect an unfamiliar landing area more
			closely at every 500-foot interval during descent and continuously below 500 feet. Fly
			a predictable landing pattern and attempt to land clear of turbulence and obstacles.
			Prepare for a PLF.
			Be polite to property owners. Cross only at gates or reinforced areas and leave all gates
			as they were found. Do not disturb livestock. Walk parallel to and between any rows
			of crops until reaching the end of the field. Repair or replace any damaged property. If
			possible, contact the drop zone to give them your status and location.
			Some skydiving schools are subject to state and local rules or restrictions concerning
			landing off. Your instructor will explain anything that pertains to you and your drop zone.	
			CANOPY DRILL: Experience a Flight Cycle
			● Release brakes and address any routine opening problems.
			● Look left, turn left.
			● Look right, turn right.
			● Flare.
			● Check altitude, position, and traffic.
			● Find the holding area, landing area and pattern-entry point.
			● Fly directly to the holding area.
			● Check altitude, position and traffic.
			● Smoothly and evenly pull toggles to ¾ brakes (hip bones) and hold for 5 seconds.
			● Quickly but smoothly raise the toggles back to full flight to induce the flight cycle.
			● Take note of the canopy surge and dive as it picks up speed.
			● Expect 5-7 seconds to pass for the canopy to recover to full flight.
			● Repeat, if altitude permits, this time with a forceful flare to get back under the
			parachute for landing (to practice your response to turbulence close to the ground).
			● Check altitude, position, and traffic.
			● Stay in the holding area until starting the pattern at 900 feet.
			● Fly the planned pattern following the landing priorities on final.
			● Flare to land and PLF
			A. Exit and Freefall
			Solo Exit
			In this category, you will perform a solo
			exit, achieving stability within 5 seconds.
			Remember tools to maintain control and
			stability, including HAALR and AIR.
			Freefall Turns
			To turn in freefall, first establish a comfortable, relaxed, neutral body position. Find
			a point ahead on the horizon as a primary
			heading reference. Use the start-coaststop (SCS) technique to control your turn.
			Turns should begin from a neutral body
			position. Maintain symmetry in your arms
			and legs, a straight spine, and level shoulders. Breathe, relax, and initiate the turn:
			Start by pressing one elbow down from
			the shoulder joint only. Press your arm
			down no more than 45 degrees. Maintain a
			neutral leg position during the turn.
			Coast in the turn by returning to neutral before your desired heading comes into view.
			Your momentum will continue to turn you while you are neutral, much like your car
			continues to go forward after taking your foot off the accelerator. During the coast,
			assess your speed and the distance to your desired heading to determine when you
			should begin your stop movement.
			Stop by countering the turn in the opposite direction, then return to a neutral
			body position.
			If you go past your intended heading or encounter other difficulties, use HAALR and
			pick a new heading before starting another turn. Stop all maneuvers by 6,000 feet.
			Rear-Riser Steering
			Learning to use your rear risers gives
			you more options to control your
			canopy. The rear risers operate the
			back half of your canopy, and steering with them with your brakes still
			stowed is the fastest way to change
			heading right after opening. Rearriser steering is the first of several
			Canopy-Flight Emergency Procedures (CEPs) you will learn, because
			it can be useful for avoiding a canopy
			collision right after opening.
			To steer with your rear risers, reach
			up and grab them firmly above
			where the toggles are stowed. Look
			in the direction you want to turn,
			check for traffic, and pull that riser
			down 4 to 6 inches. In this category,
			you will perform 90-degree rearriser turns after visually inspecting your canopy but before you unstow your toggles.
			You will perform them again with your toggles unstowed. Once you have unstowed
			your toggles, keep them in your hands while performing rear-riser maneuvers. Stop all
			rear-riser steering practice by 2,000 feet.
			Accuracy
			Flying a predictable pattern and arriving at pattern checkpoints at the proper altitude
			improves your chances of landing where you planned. Being accurate on landing builds
			your confidence in case you ever land off the drop zone. With the help of your instructor, use the forecasted ground and winds aloft to choose your pattern entry point,
			checkpoints, and target. A checkpoint includes both an altitude and a landmark.
			Before your jump, identify your
			target and draw a 165-foot (50-meter)
			radius circle around it on the aerial
			map. Use an interactive online map
			to help estimate the distance. Land
			within that area with minimal radio
			assistance and record the distance
			from the target in your logbook.
			C. Emergency
			Procedure Review
			You will review canopy problems
			and malfunctions in the training harness to help you develop
			quicker recognition of malfunctions
			and improve your decision-making
			ability, especially as your assigned pull altitude lowers as you gain experience. The
			canopy must reliably fly straight, turn, and flare. Decide if your canopy is safe to land by
			the 2,500-foot decision altitude and execute your emergency procedures if necessary.
			You should be able to describe procedures for landing on a building: If landing on
			a roof, flare and PLF. Once you’ve landed, disconnect the RSL, if able, and cut away. If
			landing your reserve, contain it. Wait for help. If hitting a building broadside, turn the
			canopy slightly to avoid a direct impact before flaring. Prepare to PLF, flare to slow
			down, and attempt to strike a glancing blow.
			Spotting, Wind Drift, and Opening Point
			You must determine the ground winds and
			winds aloft before every skydive according to the BSRs (Chapter 2-1.K). Having this
			information can help you plan your canopy
			flight and landing pattern. You can obtain
			current wind information from various
			weather apps. Ask your instructor which
			apps provide the most accurate information for your drop zone. The apps provide
			the direction and strength of the wind at
			ground level and at various altitudes in
			either miles per hour or knots. The description of winds includes their direction of
			origin expressed as a compass heading
			such as, “The ground winds are from
			two-seventy degrees.” In this example, the
			winds are blowing from the west. Thus,
			your planned landing pattern will have the
			final approach going west, facing into the
			wind for landing.
			To land on the drop zone, you must be
			able to determine the spot on the ground
			over which to exit the plane and know how
			to find that spot while on jump run in the
			aircraft. Jump run is the predetermined
			path the aircraft flies prior to exit. Your
			exit point is the point at which you exit
			the plane. The direction of jump run is determined by the strength and direction of
			the winds aloft. The stronger the winds aloft, the farther the exit point will be from
			the landing area. The wind pushes you during freefall from the exit point toward the
			landing area. This horizontal movement is known as wind drift. The winds, presence
			of clouds, the size of your group and your jump type, planned deployment altitude, and
			many other factors all go into determining your ideal exit point.
			Spotting is the term for selecting an exit point while accounting for the effect of winds
			aloft in freefall and during canopy flight. The exit point is also known as the spot. Spotting starts with determining the best opening point for canopies, which is the ground
			point of reference over which you open your parachute. This point is determined from
			wind forecasts for different altitudes. The stronger the wind is at the exit altitude and
			during freefall, the farther upwind of the holding and landing area the exit point, or
			spot, will be. This is also true for the canopy opening point, as it also should be upwind
			of your holding and landing area. If you open upwind of your holding area, the wind will
			help you get there. 
			The pilot, instructors, and drop zone staff determine the direction of jump run and the
			location of the spot based upon the forecasted and observed winds. The direction of
			jump run and the location of the spot may change throughout the day as the weather
			and winds change.
			The first step in learning to spot is determining what is “straight down” and predicting
			how the plane is moving across the ground. First, look straight out at the horizon and
			draw an imaginary line back to you. Then look forward toward where you are headed
			and draw an imaginary line back to you. The junction of the two perpendicular lines
			from the horizon marks the point straight below the aircraft. Before exiting, you must
			also verify that the area below you is clear of clouds and aircraft, and to do so effectively, you must get your head completely outside the aircraft.
			You will observe your instructor’s spotting procedures, and then you will demonstrate
			the technique for looking straight down from the aircraft during jump run. You should
			be able to determine whether the aircraft is on the intended jump run and when you
			are at your desired exit point. 
			You can note your freefall time in your logbook based on your exit altitude by assuming an average terminal velocity of 120 mph. The first 1,000 feet of your freefall takes
			approximately 10 seconds as you reach terminal velocity. Each 1,000 feet after that
			takes approximately 5 seconds. For example: You exit the airplane at 5,000 feet and
			deploy your canopy at 3,000 feet. The first 1,000 feet takes 10 seconds, and the next
			1,000 feet takes 5 seconds. You can log 15 seconds of freefall time.
			CANOPY DRILL: Rear-Riser Turns
			● Correct minor canopy problems (line twist, slider, end cells) using rear risers with brakes
			stowed.
			● Check altitude, position, and traffic.
			● Locate the holding area and turn toward it. Reach to the top of the risers and grab
			where the lines meet the risers.
			● Look right, turn right 90 degrees using rear riser.
			● Check altitude, position, and traffic.
			● Repeat to the left.
			● Check altitude, position, and traffic.
			● Repeat turns if altitude permits.
			● Unstow the brakes above 2,500 feet, do a controllability check and fly to the holding
			area.
			● With your hands in your toggles, reach to the top of the risers and grab the risers
			where the lines meet the risers.
			● Look right, turn right 90 degrees using rear riser.
			● Check altitude, position, and traffic.
			● Repeat to the left.
			● Check altitude, position, and traffic.
			● Repeat turns right and left if altitude permits.
			● Return to steering with the toggles by 2,000 feet.
			● Fly the planned pattern, flare and PLF if needed.
			Stalls
			A stall is an aerodynamic event where the wing loses its ability to produce lift. When
			a ram-air parachute stalls, it also loses pressurization, and the canopy will no longer
			be able to support the weight of the jumper. To avoid stalling close to the ground in a
			flare, you should know the stall point on any canopy you jump, especially if the canopy
			is new to you. For this reason, you need to perform all stall practice above your 2,500-foot
			decision altitude.
			Too much input or input applied too abruptly using either the toggles or the rear risers
			can cause a stall. Applying too much input is associated with a slow-speed stall, where
			the canopy loses airspeed and eventually stalls. Applying input too abruptly is associated
			with a high-speed stall, where the stall occurs more suddenly and at a higher airspeed.
			Before intentionally stalling with toggles, make sure your canopy is in full flight and
			flying straight. Slowly pull the toggles down to full arm extension until you feel the onset
			of the stall, a feeling similar to rocking back in a chair and falling backward. After holding
			the toggles all the way down for 5 to 6 seconds, the stall will develop further, and the
			canopy will become bowtie shaped. The air will leave the canopy, and you will begin
			descending at a high rate. Some student canopies are configured to prevent a toggle
			stall, so your canopy may not develop a full one. Recover from a fully developed toggle
			stall by slowly raising the toggles up a few inches until the canopy inflates and returns
			to slow flight. Avoid raising the toggles too quickly, which can cause the canopy to surge,
			dive, or spin into line twists.
			Stalling using the rear risers works similarly, except that you need to pull down only 5
			or 6 inches on both risers. For now, you will practice only toggle stalls; your B-license
			canopy training addresses rear-riser stalls.
			Adjusting the Pattern for Accuracy
			Following a predictable, well-planned landing pattern helps maintain safe traffic flow,
			reduces the risk of canopy collisions, and improves your accuracy on landing. Improving
			your accuracy increases your options for safe landing areas and lowers your stress in
			case you need to land off the drop zone.
			To refine your accuracy, make small adjustments to your pattern checkpoints over a
			series of jumps. First, plan your checkpoints and target for your first jump of the series.
			Based on where you landed on that jump, have your instructor make a suggestion on
			adjusting one or more of your checkpoints: the pattern entry point, the entry point to
			the base leg, or the entry point to your final approach. They may have you adjust either
			the altitude or the landmark of these checkpoints. Make your next jump in similar wind
			conditions with this adjustment. Keep repeating this process to refine your accuracy for
			those wind conditions. Record your checkpoints and wind conditions in your logbook in
			order to track your progress.
			Flare Techniques
			Effective flare techniques vary depending on the design and size of a parachute,
			but the basics of flaring apply to any technique. You can refine your flare technique
			by expanding on the basics using the
			following strategies:
			Being in the PLF position for landing allows
			you to maintain your heading and stay
			level in your harness during the landing
			flare. Except for small corrections on final
			approach, keep your toggles all the way
			up, in full glide, for 8 to 10 seconds before
			starting your flare. This will help the canopy
			produce more lift when you flare. Keep your chin level, looking at the point mid-way
			to the horizon, to better judge the flare height. Start the flare when your feet reach an
			altitude of approximately twice your height above the ground. Flare with your hands
			close to your body, bringing your elbows back as your hands come down. Continue
			to push your hands evenly down the side of your thighs to full arm extension. It is
			important to fully finish your flare. Finish with your feet approximately 1 to 3 feet
			above the ground. Hold the flare all the way down during a PLF or for a few steps after
			touch down.
			Two common flare techniques are the continuous flare and the staged flare. Most
			larger canopies, those 220 square feet or more, flare effectively with either technique.
			The continuous flare is one smooth motion that should take about the same time that
			it takes to count to five. You may count slower or faster depending on wind conditions
			or your sight picture. Regardless of the speed of your flare, you should time it to be
			smooth and consistent overall, responding to how your canopy is performing. 
			To find the sweet spot for the first stage of your flare, practice at a safe altitude in your
			holding area. Start with a medium-speed input and bring the toggles down to where
			your hands are even with your chest strap—this gives you a solid baseline. On each
			practice flare, adjust the speed or depth slightly to see how your canopy reacts. The goal
			is to pendulum smoothly forward under the canopy until the nose is directly above you.
			Pay attention to your hand position so you can repeat what works during your actual
			landing. Once you reach this point in your flare, pause and assess your height above
			the ground. Start the second stage of this two-stage flare when you are at the proper
			height to smoothly and fully finish the flare with your feet approximately 1 to 3 feet
			above the ground.
			Your instructor will determine the best flare technique for your canopy and practice
			with you for the landing on your next jump. You will practice finding the sweet spot
			above 2,500 feet on your next jump, even if you use a continuous flare for landing.
			Procedures for High-Wind Landings
			Winds can change from the time you leave the plane to when you are under canopy. If
			you land in high winds, PLF and then pull one toggle all the way in as quickly as possible
			until the canopy collapses. You risk injury when being dragged after landing in high
			winds. When you land and the canopy is dragging you and you cannot collapse it, disconnect your RSL, if possible, and cut away.
			Your canopy may dive or collapse behind any obstacle that generates turbulence.
			Thus, if landing in high winds, plan your final approach and choose a landing spot
			with the least potential for turbulence and the greatest distance between you and
			any obstacle
			CANOPY DRILL #2: Toggle-Stall-Point Practice
			● Check altitude, position, and traffic
			● From full flight, slowly pull the toggles down to full arm extension
			● Hold the toggles down for 5-6 seconds until you feel the onset of the stall, a feeling
			like rocking back in a chair and falling backward, which signals that you have found
			the stall point
			● As the stall develops further and the canopy begins to look like a bowtie, the air will
			leave the canopy, and you will begin descending at a high rate.
			● Recover from a fully developed toggle stall by slowly and symmetrically raising the
			toggles up a few inches until the canopy inflates and returns to slow flight
			● Continue to raise the toggles up 6 inches at a time to return to full flight
			● Repeat if altitude and position permit
			● Stop all maneuvers above your decision altitude of 2,500 feet
			● Fly the planned pattern and land within 165 feet (50 meters) of target
			● Measure your distance from the planned landing point and log it
			● Note: Some student canopies are configured to prevent a toggle stall, so even
			with your toggles down at full arm extension for more than 5-6 seconds, a full
			toggle stall may not develop.
			A. Exit and Freefall
			The Flat Track
			Before beginning to jump with others, you
			need to learn to generate horizontal speed
			with minimal altitude loss, a skill called “tracking.” This skill allows you to create separation
			from others before opening your parachute.
			You will perform a flat track, maintaining heading within 30 degrees. Focus on
			heading first, then pitch; speed will come
			with practice.
			First, locate a point on the horizon to establish your heading. Smoothly and fully extend
			both legs with your toes pointed to initiate forward motion, and steer to maintain
			heading. Roll your shoulders and flatten your
			arch to control your pitch. Fully extend your
			arms to the side, pressing them down level
			with your hips. Once you can control your
			heading and pitch, you can speed up your
			track by extending your legs more quickly
			and sweeping your arms back slightly.
			Stop your track by passing through neutral,
			extending your arms forward and down
			slightly. Return to neutral.
			Practice entering and refining an on-heading 5-second track, turning 180 degrees after
			each attempt and repeating as altitude permits. Exit from a position facing up the line
			of flight, such as a floater exit. Turn 90 degrees to start tracking perpendicularly to the
			line of flight. This allows you to avoid those who exited before or after you, up and down
			the line of flight. Always plan tracking dives with other groups in mind.
			Knowing how your canopy flies in different modes of flight can be useful for adjusting your descent. For example, flying in half brakes before you enter the pattern can
			help you stay a safe vertical distance from other canopies. Flying your downwind leg in
			half brakes can flatten your glide to conserve altitude in case you find yourself lower
			than planned. When flying in brakes, expect a different a glide path than what you
			normally experience.
			CEP—Braked Turns
			Braked turns are one of the most important canopy-flight emergency procedures
			(CEPs) you can practice. Using braked turns, also called “flat turns,” you can change
			direction under canopy while losing as little altitude as possible. A braked turn also
			slows your forward speed while maintaining a stable, level wing. If you find yourself
			landing in a tight or unfamiliar landing area and you must turn to avoid an obstacle at a
			low altitude, you can use a braked turn. In this emergency situation, executing a braked
			turn instead of a turn from full flight allows you to change heading and still honor the
			first landing priority: landing with a level wing.
			Start by pulling both toggles down evenly to the half-braked position and hold for a few
			seconds. Push one toggle down slightly to initiate a 90-degree turn. Practice changing
			heading as quickly as possible while keeping the wing level. You will practice 90-degree
			braked turns in this category, but you may need only a 45-degree turn or less, followed
			by a braked flare, to avoid an obstacle on landing.
			CEP—Half-Braked Flares
			Practicing braked flares can help you discover the effectiveness of the flare when finishing from a braked position. This CEP is useful in several situations, including when
			you initially flare too high and need to hold in brakes for a few seconds before finishing;
			after you use a braked turn to avoid an obstacle on landing; or when you turn too close
			to the ground.
			First, for reference, start by performing a flare from full flight using your normal landing
			technique. Note the pitch change of your parachute and your swing forward under the
			parachute at the bottom of your flare stroke. Start a half-braked flare by pulling the
			toggles to a half-braked position and hold for a few seconds. Then, from that position,
			flare more quickly and forcefully than you would for your normal flare stroke. Compare
			the flares you just practiced, especially the parachute’s pitch change and your swing
			forward. Practice another braked flare, adjusting the speed and force to most closely
			match the effect of your flare from full flight. Braked flares generally need to be faster
			and more forceful than a flare from full flight to get an equivalent response.
        </Section>
    </ReferenceLibrary>

	
</SkyHighSyllabus>