<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ULESchema>
    <Config>
        <course_title>SkyHigh Elementary Parachute Training</course_title>
        <overview>This course will teach you the essentials of parachuting, including the gear, jump and emergency procedures</overview>
    </Config>
    <Module name="M1: Equipment" id="CAT-GEAR">
        <Lesson id="CAT-GEAR-01" name="The Parachute Rig">
            <Context>This lesson covers the elements of the parachute rig, so you know where everything is.</Context>
            <MaxScore>100</MaxScore>
            <Multiplier>1</Multiplier>
            <LessonElements>
                <Element title="Dual canopy system">Your rig must have a main and reserve. These should be inspected yearly.</Element>
                <Element title="Main Ripcord">Located right side, chest height. Pull outwards with right-hand, not crossbody.</Element>
                <Element title="Reserve Handle">Silver Handle, Located left side, hip height.</Element>
            </LessonElements>
            <LessonResources>
                <Resource type="image" file="CAT-GEAR-01_chute_overview.jpg">Overview diagram of parachute.</Resource>
                <Resource type="image" file="CAT-GEAR-01_chute_handles.jpg">Diagram of parachute focussing on handle colour and location.</Resource>
            </LessonResources>
            <ApplicationScenario>The student is at the dropzone, and they are given a new parachute. What should they check for, and where will they find it?</ApplicationScenario>
        </Lesson>
        <Lesson id="CAT-GEAR-02" name="The Altimeter">
            <Context>This lesson looks at the altimeter.</Context>
            <Multiplier>1</Multiplier>
            <MaxScore>100</MaxScore>
            <LessonElements>
                <Element title="Check Cadence">We need to check alitmeter every 5 seconds during freefall</Element>
                <Element title="Correct Setting For Drop Zone">Always set Altimeter so that zero matches dropzone elevation.</Element>
                <Element title="Decision Window">5,000ft AGL: Start of the Decision Window, reaching down to 3,000 feet</Element>
                <Element title="Mandatory Deployment Altitude">3,000ft AGL: Essential parachute is deployed to allow time to reserve deployment in case of failure.</Element>
            </LessonElements>
            <LessonResources>
                <Resource type="image" file="CAT-GEAR-02_altimeter_example.jpg">Example image of a wrist altimeter.</Resource>
                <Resource type="image" file="CAT-GEAR-02_decision_window.jpg">Diagram of the decision window, showing altitude heights.</Resource>
            </LessonResources>
            <ApplicationScenario>The student is at 6,000 feet. What are their actions over the next few seconds?</ApplicationScenario>
        </Lesson>
    </Module>
    <Module name="M2: Environment" id="CAT-ENV">
        <Lesson id="CAT-ENV-01" name="Danger Conditions">
            <Context>This lesson highlights weather conditions that might impact or prevent a jump.</Context>
            <MaxScore>100</MaxScore>
            <Multiplier>1</Multiplier>
            <LessonElements>
                <Element title="Cumulonimmbus">These clouds cabn be lethal for jumpers due to updrafts, turbluence, rain, hail etc. Jumping is prohibited if there are cumulonimbus clouds within 10 miles of the dropzone.</Element>
                <Element title="Cloud Cover">No boarding if cloud cover is below 2,000ft AGL</Element>
                <Element title="Wind Speed at DZ">Maximum ground wind speed at drop zone of 20 knots</Element>
            </LessonElements>
            <LessonResources>
                <Resource type="image" file="CAT-ENV-01_cunim.jpg">Ref Image of cunim (thunderhead) cloud formation.</Resource>
                <Resource type="image" file="CAT-ENV-01_cloud_cover.jpg">Ref Image of low cloud over dropzone.</Resource>
                <Resource type="image" file="CAT-ENV-01_wind_speed.jpg">Ref image of windsock and anemometer.</Resource>
            </LessonResources>
            <ApplicationScenario>The student is at the dropzone, on a cloudy and blustery day. What should they check for?</ApplicationScenario>
        </Lesson>
        <Lesson id="CAT-ENV-02" name="Water Landings">
            <Context>This lesson looks at the dangers of (and correct process for) water landings.</Context>
            <Multiplier>1</Multiplier>
            <MaxScore>100</MaxScore>
            <LessonElements>
                <Element title="Dangers of Water Landing">Landing in water is a dangerous activity. Jumpers has become cocooned in the chute fabric and lines and have drowned.</Element>
                <Element title="Water Landing SOP">Airborne Action: Unclip chest strap. Water Contact Action: Unclip leg straps only upon touching water. Reasoning: Prevents harness fall-out while avoiding cocooning.</Element>
            </LessonElements>
            <LessonResources>
                <Resource type="image" file="CAT-ENV-02_water_dangers.jpg">Example image of a parachute in the water.</Resource>
                <Resource type="image" file="CAT-ENV-02_water_land_SOP.jpg">Diagram of the correct approach to a water landing.</Resource>
            </LessonResources>
            <ApplicationScenario>The student is at 1,500 feet in a coastal location. An offshore wind is blowing. What are their actions over the next few minutes?</ApplicationScenario>
        </Lesson>
    </Module>
</ULESchema>